<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>




<section xml:id="communities" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Community Detection in Gephi</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>



	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>

		<exercise>
			<title>Zachary's Karate Club</title>
			<idx><h>Zachary's Karate Club</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>

Social networks contain two kinds of information: which pairs of people are friends, and which pairs of people are not friends. Within a tight-knit group, a lack of friendship might indicate some latent conflict. This was the case in the Wayne Zachary's famous study  of a karate club (1997).

			<image width="100%" xml:id="fig-img-communities0" source="images/karate.png" />


While Zachary was looking at this club, a dispute erupted between the president (node 34) and the instructor (node 1). This led to the club splitting in two, with the membership shown as above. How well could we have predicted the fracturing of the group into two pieces, working just from this friendship network?

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Open the <c>karate.gml</c> file into Gephi using File/Open. Select the graph type as "Undirected."

					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Change the layout (lower left panel) so that you have a more informative representation. Show the node labels by clicking on the bold "T" at the bottom of the Graph panel.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Run the Modularity calculation on the Statistics tab (right panel).  Accept the default Resolution of 1.0. Run some other statistics that you find interesting.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Update the Nodes/Partition tab. Select "Modularity Class" and then "Apply." How many communities did you find? Do they look reasonable? Update other characteristics using the values you have calculated.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Run the Modularity with different Resolution values until you get exactly 2 communities. What is the first resolution value that works?

					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
  Click on the filter tab (right panel). Add an Attribute/Partition/ Modularity Class filter. Filter so that only one community is shown.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Manually separate the communities. Click on the Grabbing Hand in the left column of Graph panel. Then click on the word "<em>Dragging (Configure)</em>" at the upper left of the panel. Increase the diameter of the dragging hand. Then move all of the current community at once.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Stop the filter so that both communities are shown again. Reduce your dragging diameter to 1 and then move nodes to get a pleasing picture.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Now we are going to make a more professional network visualization. Go to the Preview view. Click "Refresh" to make the network appear. Then start playing with the Preset settings, including changing the dropdown from "Default" to some of the other choices. Make the prettiest picture that you can! You will have to click "Refresh" to apply your changes. There is an "Export" option at the lower left corner.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Dolphin Social Network</title>
			<idx><h>Dolphin Social Network</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Lusseau and Newman performed a social network analysis on a dolphin population in Doubtful Sound, New Zealand. They used Betweenness Clustering (successively removing edges with highest betweenness) to find two communities of dolphins. These are the black and non-black nodes shown in the figure to the right. The non-black community is further subdivided into 3 sub-communities, according to shade of grey. Females are represented by circles, males by triangles, and unknown gender by squares.



			<image width="60%" xml:id="fig-img-communities1" source="images/dolphin-network.png" />

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Following the same workflow as for the Zachary Karate Club, investigate this dolphin social network, which is found in the <c>dolphin.gml</c> file linked on the moodle site.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 What value of modularity do you need to use to get 2 communities? 4 communities? How do your communities (found by the Louvain method) compare the the communities found by Lusseau and Newman?
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 In the Preview view, make the most compelling graphic you can for the dolphin network. Nodes should be colored according to the four communities you found. The rest is up to you.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>



				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>US Airline Network Revisited</title>
			<idx><h>US Airline Network Revisited</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>


Let's return to the US Airline network that we explored in a previous lab. I've created a new version of this gml file so that the default layout uses the longitude and latitude to place the nodes. (The previous file displayed the US upside-down!)

Load the <c>us-airlines2.gml</c> file into Gephi. <em>Do not change the layout of the nodes</em> so that we can continue to see the geographic location of the airports. Here is what it will look like when you load it in.

			<image width="60%" xml:id="fig-img-communities2" source="images/usair.png" />

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Run some statistics on the network. Change the sizes of nodes and labels according to useful information, by your judgment.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Calculate the modularity and color the nodes according to the communities. Start  with the default Resolution = 1.0. Look at each of the communities. Is this a good separation? Should we increase or decrease the number of communities to get a meaningful separation? Do it until you have a partition of the network that "makes sense." You have to decide what to factor into that choice.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Make a beautiful layout.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>



</section>
