<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>







<section xml:id="navsmallworld" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Navigable Small World Model</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>


The Small World Model of Strogatz and Watts contains short paths, but they are very hard to find! In this activity, we study a variation of Kleinberg's Navigable Small World Model.




We start with a cycle on <m>n+1</m> vertices <m>\{0,1,2,\ldots n\}</m>. Then each vertex chooses a (one-way) "long-range contact" according to
<me>
\Pr[ u \mbox{ is } v\mbox{'s long range contact}] = C \cdot \frac{1}{d(u,v)}.
</me>
where <m>C</m> is our normalizing constant and <m>d(u,v)</m> is the ring distance between nodes <m>u</m> and <m>v</m>.



			<image width="60%" xml:id="fig-img-navsmallworld0" source="images/small-world.png" />



We consider the following greedy routing strategy from source vertex <m>s</m> to target vertex <m>t</m>:

		<ul>
			<li>
			<p>
 <em>move as close to the target as possible, either by walking on the ring edge, or following the long-range edge (when this takes us closer to <m>t</m>).</em>
			</p>
			</li>
		</ul>


Consider a journey from source vertex <m>s</m> to target vertex <m>t</m>. We will consider the "worst case" of starting at vertex <m>0</m> and trying to get to vertex <m>n/2</m>. You will show that the expected number of steps in this journey is
<me>
O \left( (\log n)^2 \right)
</me>
where <m>\log n = \log_2 n</m> is the base-2 logarithm of <m>n</m>.


			</p><p>
In order to prove this result,
we will divide our journey from <m>s</m> to <m>t</m> into phases:
		<ul>
			<li>
			<p>
 phase <m>j</m> = ring distance <m>d</m> to target vertex satisfies <m>2^j \leq d &lt; 2^{j+1}</m>.
			</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
Note that these phases are indexed in reverse.  That is, when we are far from the target <m>t</m>, our phase index is <em>larger</em>. In other words, we "count down" the phases. For example, the in the following figure, we start in Phase 3 (at source vertex <m>s</m>) and end in Phase 0 (at target vertex <m>t</m>).


			<image width="50%" xml:id="fig-img-navsmallworld1" source="images/nav-phases.png" />



Let <m>X</m> denote the total number of steps in our journey. Let <m>X_j</m> denote the number of steps taken during phase <m>j</m>. In the example above, our journey takes <m>X=5</m> steps. We have
<me>
X_3 = 1,
X_2 = 1,
X_1 = 2,
X_0 = 1.
</me>

The goal of this activity is to show that
<me>
\E[X] = \sum_{k=0}^{\log (n/2)} \E[X_k] = O\left( (\log n)^2 \right),
</me>
meaning that the expected number of steps is at most <m>K \cdot (\log n)^2</m> for some constant <m>K &gt; 0</m>. In other words, in a typical network of this kind, our journey takes at most <m>O((\log n)^2)</m> steps.

			</p><p>

Our analysis combines tools from computer science (analysis of algorithms), statistics (probability) and mathematics (calculus, combinatorics).

	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 To check your understanding, explain why the length of the journey from <m>s</m> to <m>t</m> is
<me>
X = \sum_{k=0}^{\lfloor \log (n/2) \rfloor} X_k
</me>
In other words, be sure that you understand
		<ul>
			<li>
			<p>
 how we have partitioned the journey into phases, and
			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 why the upper limit of the sum is <m>\lfloor \log (n/2) \rfloor.</m>
			</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
From here forward, we will omit the floor function from our expressions, and write
<m> \log (n/2) </m> when we actually mean <m>\lfloor \log (n/2) \rfloor</m>. We trust that you know that we need to use integer values.

			</p><p>

Okay, you now understand this formula for a given network. In the rest of this activity, we will calculate the expected length of a journey on a randomly generated network. We use linearity of expectation to write the  expected length of this journey as the sum of the expected lengths of the phases:
<me>
\E[X] = \E \left[ \sum_{k=0}^{\log (n/2)} X_k \right] =
\sum_{k=0}^{\log (n/2)} E[X_k].
</me>


<solution>
<p>
We have partitioned the journey into phases. Each step occurs in exactly one phase: when we are at a vertex that is distance <m>d</m> from the target, we are in phase <m> \lfloor \log(d) \rfloor</m>. So to get the total number of steps, we just add the number of steps taken in each phase.

Here are a couple of notes:
		<ul>
			<li>
			<p>
 The indexing of the phases "counts down": the first phase is <m>j= \lfloor \log(n/2) \rfloor </m> and the last phase is <m>j=0</m>.
			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 It is possible to have <m>X_k=0</m>.  this occurs when  we take a long range edge that jumps over the interval <m>2^k \leq d &lt; 2^{k+1}</m>.
			</p>
			</li>
		</ul>


</p>
</solution>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 The random long-range contact is chosen according to the PMF
<me>
\Pr[ v \mbox{ is } u \mbox{'s long range contact}] = C \cdot \frac{1}{d(u,v)}.
</me>
Show that the normalizing constant <m>C</m> satisfies
<me>
C &gt; \frac{1}{2\log n}
</me>
where <m>\log n= \log_2 n</m>. You will need to use the following inequalities, which you saw in your calculus classes (and might have forgotten):
<me>
\sum_{i=1}^{k} \frac{1}{i} \leq 1 +  \mbox{ln}(k)  \leq  1 + \log_2(k).
</me>


<solution>
<p>

We assume that <m>n</m> is even (for simplicity).
We have
<me>
1 =  2 \, C \, \sum_{i=1}^{n/2} \frac{1}{i} \leq   2 \, C ( 1 + \log(n/2)) = 2 \, C ( 1 + \log(n) - \log(2))  =2 C  \log(n)
</me>
and so
<me>
\frac{1}{2 \log n} \leq C
</me>

</p>
</solution>


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 Consider a vertex <m>v</m> with ring distance <m>d=d(v,t)</m> satisfying <m>2^j \leq d &lt; 2^{j+1}</m>.
			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Let
<me>
A = \{ w \mid d(w,t) \leq d/2 \}
</me>
be the set of vertices that are "at most half the distance from <m>t</m> as <m>v</m>." Explain why
<me>
|A|=d+1
</me>
and why
<me>
\frac{d}{2} \leq d(v,w) \leq \frac{3d}{2}
</me>
for all <m>w \in A</m>.

<solution>
<p>
There are <m>d+1</m> vertices in <m>A= \{ t - d/2, \ldots , t + d/2 \}</m>. Meanwhile, vertex <m>v</m> satisties <m>d(v,t)=d</m>, so the closest <m>w \in A</m> can be is <m>d(v,w)=d/2</m> and the farthest that it can be is <m>d(v,w) = 3d/2</m>.

</p>
</solution>

					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Prove that
<me>
\displaystyle{\Pr[v \mbox{'s long-range contact is in } A] \geq  \frac{1}{3 \log n}}.
</me>

<solution>
<p>
</p>
<md>
<mrow>
\Pr[v \mbox{'s long-range contact is in } A]
&amp;\geq (d+1) \cdot  C \cdot \frac{1}{3d/2}
</mrow>
<mrow>
&amp; \geq (d+1) \frac{1}{ 2 \log n}  \cdot \frac{2}{3d}
</mrow>
<mrow>
&amp; &gt; \frac{1}{ 3\log n}
</mrow>
</md>
<p>
</p>
</solution>

					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Use part (b) to prove that
<me>
\displaystyle{\Pr[\mbox{round } j \mbox{ lasts at least } i  \mbox{ steps}] \leq  \left( 1 - \frac{1}{ 3 \log n} \right)^{i-1}}.
</me>


<solution>
<p>
If <m>v</m>'s long range contact is in <m>A</m>, then we end the round after that step. So the probability that we take at least <m>i</m> steps is
<me>
\left( 1 - \frac{1}{3 \log n} \right)^{i-1}
</me>
</p>
</solution>


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 Here is very useful fact from probability. Let <m>X</m> be any random variable taking on positive integer values. We can write the expected value of <m>X</m> as
<me>
\E[X] = \sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \Pr[X \geq k].
</me>
Indeed, when <m>X</m> only takes on positive integer values, we have
<me>
\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \Pr[X \geq k] = \sum_{k=1}^{\infty} k \Pr[X = k]
</me>
and the right hand side is the definition of <m>\E[X]</m>.

			</p><p>
Use this new formula for <m>\E[X]</m> and part 3(c) to prove that
<me>
E[X_j] \leq 3 \log n.
</me>



<solution>
<p>
The expected length of a round is at most
<me>
\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \Pr[X \geq k]  = \sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \left( 1 - \frac{1}{3 \log n} \right)^{i-1}
= \frac{1}{1 - \left( 1 - \frac{1}{ 3 \log n}\right)} = 3 \log n
</me>
</p>
</solution>


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
 Use problems 1 and 4 to conclude that an average journey takes at most
<me>
O((\log n)^2)
</me>
steps.


<solution>
<p>
We have
</p>
<md>
<mrow>
\sum_{k=0}^{\log (n/2)} E[X_j]
&amp;\leq \sum_{k=0}^{\log (n/2)}\left( 3 \log n \right)
</mrow>
<mrow>
&amp;= (3 \log n) (\log n - \log 2 + 1) = 3 (\log n)^2.
</mrow>
</md>
<p>
So an average journey takes <m>O((\log n)^2)</m> steps.
</p>
</solution>


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>



</section>
